this is the first part of the first
lecture this is what you should read from
the book these are parts of chapter one
this is the agenda we will go through
the different points notice that some of them
are marked as
self-reading so that is for you to read
on your own let's start with what is an operating
system so there are different layers that
you can think of when you think about a
system or a computer together with the
users that are working with it
so you have the hardware you have the operating
system you have the set of applications that
are being run on the operating system and
then you have the different users as I
said before the operating systems stays in between
the hardware and the users here you see that it's
actually between the hardware and the different
applications/processes/
programs (we will see what is the right term
for them) that the users are interested in
now what defines an operating system is of
course in part related to the hardware that
is being used below the operating system
if you use an iPad if you use smart washing
machine you might need to have modules in
your operating system that allow
to use fingers to give input to the
hardware on the other hand on your desktop you
might have just mouse and keyboard
and you don't need to have a
touch screen so your operating system does
not need to have a module for that so the
first point here to take into account is that
we would see this many times hardware and
operating systems are thightly connected and
again this you already saw last time the operating
system as we said sits between the hardware and
the applications on
the one hand to sort of provide an easier or more
beautiful interface if you want when you want
to communicate with the hardware for input and
output to shield the user from the hardware
but at the same time the hardware from the user
or if you want a certain user from another
user when these two or more users
are using the same hardware but it also acts as
a resource manager for the different computational
units you have in your computer so the
CPU the memory and the other devices now what
is the normal life cycle of a computer?
so put in another way how does the operating
system manages devices and users this is what
I showed you last time and we saw that
you have a very fast brain in your machine but
it's pretty ``stupid'' it just takes the next
instruction and runs it
but you know that in practice of a lot
of devices they are different from printers
to monitors to keyboards, disks and
so on so the question is how do you use such
a brain to control all these things?
well the answer to that is events or interrupts
which are the entities the things that
are marking the cycles of the operating
system so the figure I showed you it's sort
of lying meaning that is not giving you the
complete picture
this one is the correct one so what the brain
does (the CPU) is to take the next instruction
and run it but it can
also decide after running an
instruction whether to take the next instruction
and run it or to check if something has happened
if there was an interrupt and based on that
go back fetching the next instruction but in
this case a different next instruction we
will discuss several times what this means
so you don't have to worry too much right now
but so that you start getting into the mood
of these things
you have to assume that the operating system
is doing some work it's running Spotify there is an interrupt
something happens might be the disk
that tells the operating system that a certain
file has been copied from the main memory
to the disk
this is an interrupt the CPU once it's done
with the current instruction that belongs
to Spotify will check what is happening and
depending on the case for example if the disk
has completed transferring something from
memory will decide what is the next instruction
that will be executed
in this sample it's a keystroke need
to print a character on the screen then it takes
the important instruction to do that the relevant
instruction and it does that one it is finished if there
is nothing more to do then it goes back to
the running Spotify
there is another interrupt the operating
system checks what is happening now
it's the disk that has done something then I will tell
the disk to copy something else I will
get another interrupt and so on I mentioned
before that you have the feeling that many
things are being run at the same time while
in practice it's
only one thing that is being run sometimes
(this is not necessarily true we will
see this) the thing is that as I said since
the brain it's extremely fast you have the
feeling that they're running at the same time
what is happening is that the operating system
is continuously switching and deciding what
is the next instruction I
should run based on the interrupts it gets